Inventory of the Levinskaia-Lesman collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Levinskaia-Lesman collection
1898-2000
2001C2
Hoover Institution Archives
25 manuscript boxes (10 linear feet)
The collection consists of serials, pamphlets, and leaflets issued by nationalist, fascist, and religious organizations in Saint Petersburg, Russia, relating to political conditions in Russia. They were collected by Irina Levinskaia and Iurii Lesman.
Levinskaia, I.A.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Irina Levinskaia is a senior research fellow at the St. Petersburg Institute of History and the former editor of Bar'er, an anti-fascist journal. Iurii Lesman is a research fellow at the State Hermitage Museum in St. Petersburg.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of serials, pamphlets, and leaflets issued by nationalist, fascist, and religious organizations in Saint Petersburg, Russia, relating to political conditions in Russia. They were collected by I.A. Levinskaia and IUrii Lesman.
An itemized list in Russian matching the item number with a title and other information created by Levinskaia may be found below.
Fascism--Russia (Federation); Nationalism--Russia (Federation); Russia (Federation)--Politics and government--1991-; Saint Petersburg (Russia); Soviet Union--Politics and government--1985-1991.
- Russian language item inventory
  Russian language item inventory
  Scope and Contents note
  An itemized list in Russian matching the item number with a title and other information created by Levinskaia.
- Dokumenty partii i organizatsii, osushchestvliavshikh svoiu deiatel'nost' na territorii Sankt-Peterburga (Documents of parties and organizations active in St. Petersburg), 1984-2000 (Box 1-7)
  Consists of serials, pamphlets, bulletins, leaflets, and posters created by political and religious groups active in St. Petersburg. Arranged by organization name in Russian alphabetical order
  - Natsional-patrioticheskie partii i organizatsii, 1984-2000
    - Aleksandr Dugin i istoriko-religioznaia organizatsiia "Arktogeia,", 1993 and 1995 (Folder 1: 1-2)
    - Vsemirnyi antisionistskii front. Vsesoiuznyi antisionistskii front. Patrioty. A.Z. Romanenko, 1989-1991 (Folder 1: 3-8)
    - Vserossiiskaia partiia monarkhicheskogo tsentra, 1993-1994 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Dukhovnyi soiuz "Tezaurus." Dobrovol'noe obshchestvo "Oazis." Sankt-Peterburgskii Muzhskoi Klub. AO "LPK Vita." Grazhdanskoe ob"edinenie "Rossy." Russkoe osvoboditel'noe dvizhenie (ROD). Russkaia Druzhina, 1992-1994 and undated (Folder 1: 10-25)
    - Initsiativnyi obshchestvennyi komitet "V zashchitu Leningrada,", 1991 (Folder 1: 26)
    - Istoriko-kul'turnoe prosvetitel'skoe obshchestvo "Soiuz Venedov,", 1990-1995 (Folder 1: 27-30, Folder 2: 31-36)
    - Leningradskaia oblastnaia pisatelskaia organizatsiia SP RSFSR, 1990-1994 (Folder 2: 37-42)
    - Leningradskoe otdelenie Vserossiiskogo fonda kultury, 1990 (Folder 2: 43)
    - Leningradskoe russkoe patrioticheskoe dvizhenie "Otechestvo,", 1989-1992 (Folder 2: 44-49)
    - Liberal'no-Demokraticheskoe partiia Rossii, 1992-1999 (Folder 2: 50-57)
    - Narodnoe dvizhenie "K Bogoderzhaviiu,", 1997 (Folder 2: 58)
    - Narodno-osvoboditel'noe dvizhenie "Nashi,", 1994-1996 (Folder 2: 59, Folder 3: 60-62)
    - Narodno-sotsial'naia partiia, 1992-1993 (Folder 3: 63-64)
    - Natsional'no-demokraticheskaia partiia (NDP). Petrogradskaia regional'naia organizatsiia, 1989-1993 (Folder 3: 65-70)
    - Natsional'no-respublikanskaia partiia Rossii (NRPR), 1990-1995 (Folder 3: 71-81)
    - NPF "Pamiat',", 1987-1992
      - Patrioticheskoe ob"edinenie "Pamiat',", 1987-1988 (Folder 3: 82-83)
      - Natsional'no-patrioticheskii front ?Pamiat'? do raskola, 1988 (Folder 3: 84-85)
      - Natsional'no-patrioticheskii front "Pamiat'" posle raskola, 1988 (Folder 3: 86-90)
      - Russkii natsional'no-patrioticheskii front "Pamiat',", 1988-1992 (Folder 4: 91-96)
      - Razlichnye moskovskie gruppy "Pamiati,", 1988-1989 (Folder 4: 97-98)
    - "Nevskaia stanitsa." Kazaki, 1991-1996 (Folder 4: 99-102)
    - Obshchestvennyi "Komitet spaseniia Nevy-Ladogi-Onegi,", 1990 (Folder 4: 103)
    - Obshchestvennyi komitet v zashchitu Serbii i Chernogorii, 1993-1995 (Folder 4: 104-105)
    - Ob"edinenie "Sovest',", 1989 (Folder 4: 106)
    - Organizatsiia osvobozhdeniia Rossii ot evreiskoi okkupatsii, circa 1990 (Folder 4: 107)
    - Peterburgskii Fond vozrozhdeniia monarkhii, 1995 (Folder 4: 108)
    - Petrovskaia akademiia nauk i iskusstv (PANI), 1995-1997 (Folder 4: 109-111)
    - Progressivnaia partiia Vozrozhdeniia, undated (Folder 4: 112)
    - Prosvetitel'skoe obshchestvo "Za sotsializm" Kuibyshevskogo raiona Leningrada, 1994 (Folder 4: 113)
    - Rossiiskaia konstitutsionno-demokraticheskaia fraktsiia partii "Demokraticheskii soiuz,", 1988 (Folder 4: 114)
    - Rossiiskii Imperskii Soiuz-Orden, 1984 (Folder 4: 115)
    - Rossiiskii khristiansko-monarkhicheskii soiuz, 1992-1994 (Folder 4: 116-120)
    - Russkaia partiia, 1991-1999 (Folder 4: 121-123)
    - Russkaia partiia, 1991-1999 (contd.) (Folder 5: 124-129)
    - Russkaia sotsial'naia partiia, 1994 (Folder 5: 130)
    - Russkii natsional'no-patrioticheskii tsentr (RNPTs), 1989-1990 (Folder 5: 131)
    - Russkii Natsional'nyi Sobor (RNS), 1982, 1992-1995 (Folder 5: 132-140)
    - Russkoe kul'turno-prosvetitel'skoe obshchestvo "Rus',", 1994 (Folder 5: 141)
    - Russkoe natsional'noe edinstvo (RNE), 1999 and undated (Folder 5: 142-144)
    - Sankt-Peterburgskii Monarkhicheskii Soiuz, 1990 (Folder 5: 145)
    - Smol'nyi universitet, 1999-2000 (Folder 5: 146-147)
    - Soiuz nezavisimykh zhurnalistov, 1990 (Folder 5: 148)
    - Studencheskoe dobrovol'noe ob"edinenie po sokhraneniiu russkogo natsional'nogo kul'turnogo dostoianiia "Feniks,", 1989 (Folder 5: 149)
  - Kommunisticheskie i blizkie k nim partii i organizatsii, 1989-2000
    - Vsesoiuznaia kommunisticheskaia partiia bol'shevikov (VKPB), 1992-1993 (Folder 5: 150-157)
    - Kommunisticheskaia partiia Rossiiskoi Federatsii, (KPRF), 1991-2000 (Folder 5: 158, Folder 5: 159-164)
    - Konfederatsiia anarkho-sindikalistov (KAS), 1993 (Folder 6: 165)
    - Obshchestvenno-politicheskoe ob"edinenie Leningrada i Leningradskoi oblasti ?Kommunisty za prava grazhdan,?, 1993-1995 (Folder 6: 166-168)
    - Ob"edinennyi front trudiashchikhsia (OFT), 1989-1997 (Folder 6: 169-171)
    - Rossiiskaia Kommunisticheskaia pabochaia partiia (RKRP), 1992-1996 (Folder 6: 172-180)
    - Rossiiskaia partiia kommunistov (RPK), 1993-1997 (Folder 6: 181-182)
    - Trudovaia Rossiia. Trudovoi Leningrad, 1995-1997 (Folder 6: 183-189)
    - Trudovaia Rossiia. Trudovoi Leningrad, 1995-1997 (contd.) (Folder 7: 190-193)
    - Federatsiia profsoiuzov Sankt-Peterburga, 1994 (Folder 7: 194)
  - Religioznye organizatsii, 1993-1996
    - Deiatel'nost' novykh religioznykh techenii v Sankt-Peterburge, 1994 (Folder 7: 195)
    - Pravoslavnaia tserkov' protiv nepravoslavnykh religioznykh techenii, 1993-1996 (Folder 7: 196-199)
  - Izdaniia i dokumenty monarkhicheskoi napravlennosti, 1991 (Folder 7: 200-201)
  - Izdaniia i dokumenty natsionalisticheskoi napravlennosti, 1989-1995 (Folder 7: 202-211)
  - Sovmestnye zaiavleniia riada organizatsii, 1987-1994 (Folder 7: 212-213)
- Periodicheskie izdaniia, rasprostraniavshiesia v Sankt-Peterburge (Periodicals circulated in St. Petersburg), 1989-1999 (Box 7-20)
  Consists of newspapers and magazines published by monarchist, nationalist, communist, and religious groups. Arranged by organization type and thereunder in Russian alphabetical order
  - Natsional-patrioticheskie periodicheskie izdaniia, 1989-1999
    - Zarubezhnye periodicheskie monarkhicheskie izdaniia, 1989-1993 (Folder 7: 214-215)
    - Izdavaemaia v Sankt-Peterburge i rasprostraniaemaia aktivistami natsional'no-patrioticheskikh organizatsii periodika, v vykhodnykh dannykh kotoroi ne oboznachena sviaz' s etimi organizatsiiami, 1993-1999 (Folder 7: 216-221, Folder 8: 222-240)
    - Moskovskie natsionalisticheskie periodicheskie izdaniia, 1990-1996 (Folder 9: 241-256)
    - Moskovskie natsionalisticheskie periodicheskie izdaniia, 1990-1996 (contd.) (Folder 10: 257-285)
    - Moskovskie natsionalisticheskie periodicheskie izdaniia, 1990-1996 (contd.) (Folder 11: 286-302)
    - Regional'nye natsionalisticheskie periodicheskie izdaniia, 1991-1995 (Folder 11: 303-311)
    - Regional'nye natsionalisticheskie periodicheskie izdaniia, 1991-1995 (contd.) (Folder 12: 312-316)
  - Izdaniia s natsionalisticheskim uklonom, 1991-1993
    - Sankt-Peterburgskie, 1991-1993 (Folder 12: 317-319)
    - Regional'nye, 1992 (Folder 12: 320)
  - Kommunisticheskie i blizkie k nim, 1992-1996
    - Izdavaemaia v Sankt-Peterburge i rasprostraniaemaia aktivistami kommunisticheskikh organizatsii periodika, v vykhodnykh dannykh kotoroi ne oboznachena sviaz' s etimi organizatsiiami, 1992-1996 (Folder 12: 321-331)
    - Moskovskaia kommunisticheskaia pressa, 1992-1996 (Folder 12: 332-339)
    - Moskovskie i regional'nye gazety Rossiiskoi Kommunisticheskoi rabochei partii, 1992-1994 (Folder 13: 340-342)
    - Periodicheskie izdaniia "proletartistov,", 1992-1994 (Folder 13: 343-345)
    - Regional'naia kommunisticheskaia pressa, v vykhodnykh dannykh kotoroi ne oboznachena sviaz' s konkretnymi organizatsiiami, 1993-1994 (Folder 13: 346-348)
    - Regional'nye gazety Vsesoiuznoi kommunisticheskoi partii bol'shevikov (VKPB), 1993-1995 (Folder 13: 349-356)
    - Regional'nye gazety Vsesoiuznoi kommunisticheskoi partii bol'shevikov (VKPB), 1993-1995 (contd.) (Folder 14: 357-360)
  - Konservativno-pravoslavnaia i pravoslavno-natsionalisticheskaia periodika, 1991-1997
    - Peterburgskaia, 1991-1997 (Folder 14: 361-367)
    - Moskovskaia i regional'naia, 1992-1993 (Folder 14: 368-370)
  - Natsionalisticheskie i konservativno-pravoslavnye periodicheskie izdaniia, poluchennye po podpiske, 1993-1999 (Folder 14: 371-373)
  - Natsionalisticheskie i konservativno-pravoslavnye periodicheskie izdaniia, poluchennye po podpiske, 1993-1999 (contd.) (Folder 15: 374-388)
  - Natsionalisticheskie i konservativno-pravoslavnye periodicheskie izdaniia, poluchennye po podpiske, 1993-1999 (contd.) (Folder 16: 389-403, Folder 15: 374-388)
  - Natsionalisticheskie i konservativno-pravoslavnye periodicheskie izdaniia, poluchennye po podpiske, 1993-1999 (contd.) (Folder 17: 404-417)
  - Natsionalisticheskie i konservativno-pravoslavnye periodicheskie izdaniia, poluchennye po podpiske, 1993-1999 (contd.) (Folder 18: 418-431)
  - Natsionalisticheskie i konservativno-pravoslavnye periodicheskie izdaniia, poluchennye po podpiske, 1993-1999 (contd.) (Folder 19: 432-438)
  - Natsionalisticheskie periodicheskie izdaniia, poluchennye ot izdatel'ia, 1992-1999 (Folder 19: 439-444)
  - Natsionalisticheskie periodicheskie izdaniia, poluchennye ot izdatel'ia, 1992-1999 (contd.) (Folder 20: 445)
  - Problemy mezhnatsional'nykh otnoshenii, kommunisticheskogo dvizheniia i konfessional'nykh organizatsii v moskovskikh i regional'nykh malotirazhnykh periodicheskikh izdaniiakh, 1990-1993 (Folder 20: 446)
- Neperiodicheskie izdaniia, rasprostraniavshiesia v Sankt-Peterburge (Non-periodicals circulated in St. Petersburg), 1898-1997 (Box 20-22: 446)
  Consists of pamphlets, books, leaflets, newspapers inserts, and brochures published by religious, communist, and nationalist groups. Includes reprints of Russian nationalist literature from before 1917. Arranged in Russian alphabetical order by author or title
  - Konservativno-pravoslavnaia i pravoslavno-natsionalisticheskaia literatura, 1992-1994 (Folder 20: 447-457)
  - Otechestvennaia kommunisticheskaia literatura, 1991-1997 (Folder 20: 458-463)
  - Otechestvennaia kommunisticheskaia literatura, 1991-1997 (Folder 21: 464)
  - Otechestvennaia nationalisticheskaia literatura, 1990-1993 (contd.) (Folder 21: 465-478)
  - Pereizdaniia otechestvennoi dorevoliutsionnoi natsionalisticheskoi literatury, 1898-1915 (Folder 21: 479-484)
  - Pereizdaniia emigrantskoi literatury natsionalisticheskogo kharaktera, 1917-1920, 1927, 1956, 1992-1995 (Folder 22: 485-492)
- Materialy predvybornykh kampanii (Election campaign materials), 1990-2000 (Box 22-25: 485-492)
  Consists of flyers, newspapers, clippings, and pamphlets relating to Russian national and St. Petersburg local elections. Arranged by election and ordered chronologically
  - Vybory deputatov Verkhovnogo Soveta RSFSR i deputatov Lengorsoveta, 1990 (Folder 22: 493-499)
  - Vybory deputatov Verkhovnogo Soveta RSFSR i deputatov Lengorsoveta, 1990 (contd.) (Folder 23: 500-504)
  - Vybory prezidenta RSFSR, 1991 (Folder 23: 505)
  - Vybory mera Leningrada, 1991 (Folder 23: 506)
  - Vybory v Gosudarstvennuiu Dumu RF i referendum po proektu Konstitutsii, 1993 (Folder 23: 507-513)
  - Vybory v Gorodskoe Sobranie Sankt Peterburga, 1994 (Folder 23: 514-523)
  - Vybory v Gosudarstvennuiu Dumu RF, 1995 (Folder 23: 524-540)
  - Vybory v Gosudarstvennuiu Dumu RF, 1995 (contd.) (Folder 24: 541)
  - Vybory Gubernatora Sankt-Peterburga, 1996 (Folder 24: 542-552)
  - Vybory Prezidenta Rossii, 1996 (Folder 24: 553-557)
  - Vybory v organy mestnogo samoupravleniia Sankt-Peterburga, 1997 (Folder 24: 558-564)
  - Vybory v Gosudarstvennuiu Dumu RF, 1999 (Folder 24: 565-570)
  - Vybory Prezidenta Rossii, 2000 (Folder 24: 571-572)
  - Vybory gubernatora Sankt-Peterburga, 2000 (Folder 24: 573-574)
  - Vybory gubernatora Sankt-Peterburga, 2000 (contd.) (Folder 25: 575-577)
  - Vybory gubernatora Sankt-Peterburga, 2000 (contd.) (Box 25: 575-577)
- Vspomogatel'nye materialy (Supplementary materials), 1989-1999
  Consists of newspapers, leaflets, clippings, pamphlets, and books published by democratic and anti-fascist groups in St. Petersburg. Arranged in categories such as anti-Fascist, Jewish, and human rights publications
  - Antifashistskie, antinatsionalisticheskie periodicheskie izdaniia, listovki, 1995 (Folder 25: 578-579)
  - Rabochie materialy po protivodeistviiu fashizmu, natsionalizmu, natsional'noi diskriminatsii, 1989-1994 (Folder 25: 580-582)
  - Obshchie problemy zashchity prav cheloveka, prav natsional'nykh men'shinstv i prochie, 1994-1999 (Folder 25: 583-584)
  - Materialy demokraticheskikh i blizkikh k nim partii i organizatsii, 1989-1997 (Folder 25: 585-592)
  - Evreiskie izdaniia, posviashchennye problemam borby s antisemitizmom, 1990-1997 (Folder 25: 593-595)
  - Otdel'nye dokumenty, 1989-1995 (Folder 25: 596-609)
  - Materialy, poluchennye iz drugikh gorodov, 1988-1991 (Folder 25: 610-611)
  - Biblioteka pri arkhive, 1982, 1990 (Folder 25: 612-613)